[music]
Hi friends. Today we're going to crochet
Star Baby, a Waldorf inspired crochet
doll that's low sew and quick to work
up. [snorts] If you prefer written
instructions, I have a printable PDF
pattern available, which even includes
bonus instructions on how to add a bit
of hair to your doll. This Amigroomi
makes a really sweet gift or craft fair
product. As a disclaimer, if you're
making this for a baby or young child,
do not use plastic safety eyes as they
can be a choking hazard. Embroider the
eyes with thread or fine yarn instead.
For this project, you will need bulky
weight five Chanel velvet yarn, a 5mm
and a 7mm crochet hook, 8 mm plastic
safety eyes, or a black embroidery
thread for embroidering the eyes,
stuffing, yarn needle, and scissors.
Let's start the head and inner body
using the 5mm crochet hook and skin tone
yarn. You can start off round one with a
chain two method where you insert eight
single crochets in the second chain from
your hook or you can use the magic ring
method that I'll be doing here. First,
you're going to make the slip knot for
the magic ring.
And then you are going to insert the
single crochets in the ring. I'm going
to insert the eight single crochets.
That's one
5 6
7 and 8.
Then I'm going to tighten the ring.
And that is that for round number one.
For round two, we are going to increase
all the way around. So, inserting your
hook into that very first stitch, we're
going to make an increase by putting in
two single crochets in the same stitch.
That's one and two.
Let's repeat around. Here's my second
increase. One and two single crochets.
Here's my third increase.
Here is my fourth increase.
fifth increase
and 8.
After you finish round two, we're going
to move on to round number three. At
this point, if you'd like to add a
little yarn scrap to keep track of where
the start of your rounds is, um that
would be a nifty idea. Otherwise, um, a
stitch marker also works really well. Or
if you're good at keeping track
mentally, you can do that as well, of
course. So, for round number three,
we're going to single crochet and then
increase, repeating that around.
Single crochet,
increase in the next stitch,
repeating that around, single crochet,
and increase. And you're going to repeat
this for a total of eight times, coming
out with 24 single crochets at the end,
or 24 stitches, excuse me.
After that, you are going to move on to
round four. For round four to eight, all
you're going to do is single crochet
around. So, here um and you can move
your stitch marker up if you'd like, but
you're simply going to insert one single
crochet in each stitch around. And what
that does is create um the length for
the doll's head. You're going to get a
long um shape now instead of just a flat
circle.
And we are going to meet back at the end
of round eight.
Again, just insert one single crochet in
each stitch around for the next few
rounds.
Here's a look at round number eight
complete. Counting from where I placed
the stitch marker for four. That's four,
five, 6, 7, and 8. And now what we're
going to do is start round nine. And
round nine is going to involve a
decrease. We're going to first single
crochet. And in the next stitch, we're
going to make a decrease.
So that's single crocheting two stitches
together.
Repeat that around. Single crochet and
then decrease.
Single crochet
and decrease.
And we're going to repeat around for a
total of 16 stitches.
For the eyes, you have a couple
different options here. In this baby,
um, I used 8 mm eyes and I spaced them
five stitches apart. And in this baby,
I'm going to be using 7 mm eyes, so
slightly smaller, and spacing them four
stitches apart. And the way I count is
by moving um here. Let's count from
here. So here is the hole for the first
eye. We're going to go four stitches
over. That's one 2 three and four. Like
so. And I do place uh both of them
between round six and seven. Counting
from the from the top. That's 1 2 3 4 5
6 and seven. So between six and seven
would be the eye placement. Now you're
welcome to change it up. Use any size
eye you want and space it as far or as
close apart as you'd like. And you can
even choose different uh rounds to put
them in. But here's what um here's an
example of what it would look like if
you follow my instructions.
Now, once you're happy with the
placement of the eyes, go ahead and
secure the backings, and then we'll move
on to the next round. I forgot to
mention, after round number nine, it's a
good time to stuff your Amigurumi's
head. So, let's go ahead and um stuff
the head before we move on.
And for the next round, we're simply
going to decrease all the way around.
So, that's going to be eight decreases
in total. Here's my first decrease.
Number two.
Number three.
Number four.
number five,
number six,
and number seven.
And last but not least, number eight.
All right, so that's eight decreases all
the way around.
For this next round, we're simply going
to single crochet all the way around.
So, insert one single crochet in each of
those eight decreases.
That's going to give you eight single
crochets total.
And now we're going to increase all the
way around. So in that first um single
crochet here, I'm going to insert two
stitches.
Here's an increase
and increase in the next stitch.
Increase in the third,
etc.
You're going to notice your amigroomi is
going to have a neck now. And here is
where the inner body is forming.
And now for rounds 13 to 19, you're
simply going to single crochet around
putting one single crochet in each
stitch. And again, um, using a stitch
marker or a yarn scrap to keep track of
your rounds would be really helpful. I'm
putting it right at the start of round
13 here, where I, um, am going to count
up all the way till 19.
So, let's go ahead um, and meet back at
the end of round 19.
Here's a look at round 19 complete.
counting from the um stitch marker at
round 13. That's 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18,
and 19. So now um before we finish off
the um groomy's body, we're going to
stuff it with um some fiberfill.
Let's go ahead and finish off with the
last round. For round 20, we're just
going to simply decrease around. So,
here's my first decrease,
and it's going to be a total of eight
repetitions.
Here's number two.
Number three.
Number four.
Five.
and eight.
And after you finish round 20, you can
go ahead and fasten off with a long
tail. You are going to be using that
long tail to sew the opening of the body
closed. So, um, let me show you how I
like to do it. Um, it's very easy.
You're going to first attach a yarn
needle
and then you're going to simply make a
running stitch all the way around in the
front loops only. So here I'm going in
the first front loop and out the next.
Keep the tail loose and um relax for
now. In and out those front loops. In
and out
and in and out. So that takes us to um
the whole round. And now as I pull that
yarn tail tight, it will cinch closed
neatly
like so.
And now all you have to do is to weave
in the end.
And as a tip, if your doll's body is a
little bit um lopsided or caved in or
dented [clears throat] in certain areas
due to the crocheting or sewing, you can
go ahead and just puff it right back up
with a yarn needle. something really
thin that'll help you um move into the
stitches without um ma making the
stitches too large. So, here is what the
head and the inner body looks like
finished.
And it's time to move on to the next
part.
For this star, you are going to be using
a 7 mm crochet hook with the yellow
yarn. To begin, we're going to start
round one with a magic ring. In the
magic ring, we're going to insert eight
single crochets. Here's my slip knot to
begin. And now here's one
and 8.
And now we're going to pull the ring
tight.
After you do that, we're going to begin
on round two. For round two, we're
simply going to increase all the way
around. So, going into the first stitch,
I'm going to insert two single crochets.
In this next stitch, I'm also going to
insert two single crochets.
and continue increasing by inserting two
single crochets in each stitch around.
You'll be going from eight stitches to
16.
After you finish round two, it's time to
move on to round number three. For round
three, we're going to single crochet and
then increase all the way around. I'm
just going to use a scrap of thread or
yarn here to keep track of where the
start of my round is. You can use a cute
little stitch marker, too, if you'd
like.
So here, that's one single crochet and
then increase in this next stitch.
Oops.
Then repeat that around. One single
crochet
and then increase in the next stitch.
One single crochet and increase.
As we repeat this all the way around,
you'll end up with um 24 stitches at the
That's that for round number three. For
round four, we're going to single
crochet twice and then increase,
repeating that all the way around. So
single crochet two
and then increase in the next stitch,
single crochet two,
then increase,
and then increase.
And as you go around, you will end up
with a total of 32 stitches.
Here's
a look at round number four complete.
After you finish that, you are going to
snip off the end for your first circle
and then [clears throat]
make a second circle without fastening
off. So here, let me just pull out that
yarn end. Okay. And now we're going to
continue um with yarn attached to the
second circle to make the arm of the
star while joining to the first circle.
Let's go ahead and smooth out this
little bump here. Let's make that a
smooth transition. So, skipping that
first uh stitch, we're going to insert
our hook from back to front in the
second stitch.
Pull the yarn through here.
like so. And then insert your hook into
that last stitch.
So here, let me show you. Here's that
last stitch. And you're going to go back
to front through that back loop only,
like so. And we're going to pull this
yarn in through.
And what it does is create a fake stitch
on the very top of that first stitch.
So, it's not adding or um taking away
any stitches here. Our stitch count is
still the same. It just makes for a
smoother transition.
Each limb will take up seven stitches of
space. There will be four limbs total,
two arms and two little legs. [snorts]
And let me show you um just really
quickly by marking the circle what that
will look like. So if I count from here,
the first stitch, that's 1 2 3 4 5 6 7.
So right here is going to be the end of
the first arm.
Take up this much space. And then in
this next one,
let me just pull that through.
We will count one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven.
And this will be the next limb.
And then coming out of that next stitch,
we're going to count seven more.
So 1 2 3 four five six seven.
And coming out of this last one, seven
more.
1 2 3 4 5 6 7.
That will leave us with four stitches at
the very end. And the four stitches are
going to be for the head.
All right. So, um if I come out of here
for the front.
So, here as you can see I have quickly
marked the placement for the arms and
legs. Here are seven stitches for the um
for one little limb, seven stitches for
another limb, seven stitches for another
limb, and seven stitches for another
limb. So, a total of 28 stitches will be
used for the all four limbs. There's
going to be four remaining up here.
That's where we'll put the head in.
All right. So, now without fastening off
for um that second circle, we're going
to crochet over
um for the arm and connect to the um
first circle we made. Let me show you
how that's done.
So here I'm going to single crochet
seven. That's one 2
5 Oops.
six and seven.
Let's go ahead and combine the two
circles together so that we can make the
first arm. Now, just place the wrong
sides of the circles together.
And it doesn't really matter where um
the start of your second um circles
round is because that is since you've
got that smooth transition going, it
will be relatively seamless.
All right. So, now that I've single
crocheted seven for that first limb, I'm
going to come to turn my piece so that
I'm now looking at the second um excuse
me, the first circle I made.
And I'm going to insert my hook into one
of the stitches in that circle.
And I'm going to now single crochet
seven.
So that's one
7.
Oops.
And then here's the fun part.
[clears throat] Make sure your circles
are lined up.
And remember, we're going to be working
in rounds for the limbs. So, counting
back uh 1 2 3 4 5 6 7. All right. This
was the first stitch I started with
um on the second circle side. So, I'm
going to go into that first stitch that
I had started with. Making sure I have
seven on one side and seven on the back.
[clears throat]
And then I'm going to make a single
crochet here.
And that's the first single crochet of
round two of the limb.
For round two, we're going to single
crochet five and then decrease two times
around. So I have I had made that first
single crochet already for round two.
Now for we're going to do the second
single crochet.
Third, fourth,
fifth,
and a decrease.
And now we're going to repeat that. So
single crochet one. Oops.
and a decrease.
Now for round three, we're going to
single crochet all the way around. So
that's 12 single crochets around
11 and 12.
And then we're going to decrease for the
next round. Single crochet two and then
decrease three times around.
One, two,
and then decrease. [clears throat]
One, two, and then decrease.
One, two,
and decrease.
Now we're going to just single crochet
around.
One 2 3
6 7
and now single crochet and decrease
three times around. One single crochet.
One decrease.
One single crochet.
And a decrease.
All right.
And at this point, um, with seven
stitches left in your, excuse me, six
stitches left in the round, we are going
to fasten off and we're going to sew the
opening closed.
You can use a yarn needle to quickly sew
up the opening.
How I like to do it is to go through um
[clears throat] the front loops of the
last round. So, I'll go put a running
stitch through by going into the first
front loop, out the next front loop,
in the next front loop, out to the next,
and then in and out.
And then as you tighten it, you'll
notice it cinches up to be a neat little
closure.
And you can weave that yarn end into the
body. [clears throat]
With the first limb finished, we're
going to start on the second one. Now,
um, as you can see, the first one ended
here, and the next one is going to start
in the next stitch. Now, I'm going to
first pull some yarn through from the
previous or the last stitch of the
previous slim.
And by doing so, I minimize this little
gap that's going to come out between my
two limbs here. You'll see it in a bit.
And leave a bit of a yarn tail so that
you can use it for sewing the gap if you
want.
And now starting in that first stitch,
see I'm in the previous one here. I'm
going to start in the first stitch. Now
here [clears throat] I'm going to single
crochet seven. 1 2 3
and 7.
And now we're going to cross over to the
other side. Make sure you have seven
open stitches closest to the U previous
limb. So that's one, two, three, four,
five, six,
seven.
So, I want to go in right here.
And then I'm going to single crochet
seven.
One
6.
Oops. And seven.
And that's that for round number one.
For round two, you're going to cross on
over back to the first stitch you made
in round one.
Yep. So, I'm going to It's a little
loose here. I'm going to pull it tight.
So, going into that first stitch in
round one [clears throat]
here,
I'm going to begin round two. Round two
is single crochet five. 1 2 3 4 5 and
then a decrease.
And let's repeat that around
for a second time. 1 2
4 and 5 and a decrease.
For round three, we're going to single
crochet around. One 2 3 4
12.
And now we're going to single crochet
two and then decrease three times
around.
Let's do that. Single crochet one, two,
and three.
And a decrease. Oops, I'm sorry. Single
crochet two and then a decrease. I went
one too far. [clears throat]
So decrease,
single crochet two,
decrease,
and decrease.
Now we're going to single crochet all
the way around. That's nine stitches
total. So that's one, two,
8, and nine.
And then after that, we're going to um
single crochet and then decrease three
times around.
Single crochet decrease.
Single crochet
decrease.
and decrease.
And again, when you finish that, you're
going to fasten off and go ahead and sew
up the opening of that limb.
And I just want to show you what the gap
looks like between the two limbs.
You can go ahead and use a yarn tail,
like a leftover yarn tail, to just sew
it up.
want to make sure that it's sewn up so
that it doesn't look funky.
Let's see. And I just do it pretty
simply by stitching the four um stitches
near the opening together
[clears throat]
and secure it with a couple stitches
before weaving in the end.
And once more, we're going to repeat u
for the second limb here.
After crocheting three limbs on the
star, you can go ahead and place the
baby's head and body into the star. So,
I'm going to just put it right here
against the very um edge of one of the
limbs.
like so.
And that body is going to go straight
down.
And now we're going to crochet the very
last limb of your star baby. Again,
we're going to attach yarn to the very
side of um or to the last stitch of the
previous slim
and start in that first stitch.
It's the next one over here.
Remember to single crochet seven along
the limb. So, that was one single
crochet.
Here's two.
Here's three,
four,
five, six,
and seven.
And now with the baby's head or in the
excuse me, with the baby's body inside
the star, we are going to now uh flip
over to the other side. We're going to
crochet in the back. Count seven
stitches over. One, two, three, four,
five, six, seven. And that's the one I'm
going to insert my hook into.
So here I'm going to crochet one
7.
And again, we're going to start round
two um by crossing over, working into
that first single crochet made in round
one.
And continue crocheting until you finish
the fourth limb.
Here's a look with all four limbs
complete. At this point, we're going to
go ahead and secure the area around the
head by [snorts] um stitching.
By the way, get some yarn and a yarn
needle for this section. We're going to
stitch around making a running stitch
over the front loops of
the um opening. So, I'm just
doing
um stitches in and out.
here. It doesn't have to be um super
precise.
All right. And after making running the
stitches all around, I'm going to pull
the yarn tail. And that's going to cinch
up the opening of the neck.
After you tighten the neck um hole
around the head, we're going to finish
it off with um a couple stitches to
secure the head. And I'm simply going to
insert
my yarn needle into the head direct or
into the neck area directly
and attaching it to the
star.
By doing so, you are going to make sure
that your doll's head and body will not
become loose and fall out eventually.
And when you've gone through enough
times, you're going to simply weave in
the ends.
And that's that for the body. As you can
see, the cute little star portion is
complete. Now, all we have left is to
make the little hat.
For the hat, you're going to use yellow
yarn and the 7 mm hook.
Begin with a magic ring. And in the
magic ring, we're going to insert six
single crochets.
Here's the slip knot to begin. And now
here's one 2
5 and six.
And we're going to go ahead and tighten
the ring.
After that, we're going to single
crochet um two and then increase,
repeating that around two times. So,
here we're going to single crochet in
each of the first two stitches.
One and two. Oops.
And then in the next stitch, I'm going
to make an increase.
Let's repeat that single crochet two
and an increase.
Now in round number two, we're going to
single crochet three and then increase,
repeating that around twice.
That is one and two and increase.
one and two and then increase.
And now we're going to single crochet
four and then increase. Repeating that
around twice.
1 2 3
and increase.
And then one 2
and an increase.
You can turn your piece inside out.
And let's continue on. Now for round
number five, we're going to single
crochet five and then increase.
Repeating that around twice.
Here's one 2 3 4
5 single crochets
and then the increase.
1 2 3 4
five single crochets and an increase.
And now we're going to do um round
number se uh six, excuse me, single
crochet six and an increase. Repeating
that around twice.
1 2 3
6 and an increase.
One 2
3 4
five
six and an increase.
Now we're going to do round number
seven. Single crochet seven and then
increase. Repeating that twice.
1 2 3 4
5 6 and seven
and increase in that next stitch.
Repeat that again.
1 2 3
and increase in that next stitch.
Now round eight, we're going to go ahead
and single crochet twice and then
increase, repeating that around six
times.
So, one, two,
two single crochets. And here's my
increase.
Repeat that. One, two, and increase.
Now for round nine uh to the end, we're
going to simply single crochet around in
each stitch. So place a yarn marker or
stitch marker if you'd like and go ahead
and just put one single crochet on top
of each stitch.
And we'll meet back at the end.
Here is round 11 complete. And at this
point we can finish with a slip stitch
at the very end. So, in that next
stitch, I'm going to do a slip stitch
here and fasten off with a long tail.
You will need a long tail because you
will be sewing the hat onto the head.
So, give yourself a generous amount to
work with.
And before I do that, I'm going to pull
in this yarn tail here. Got to hide
that.
And now let's go ahead and place the hat
over the doll's head. I like to have the
uh fasten off or the start of the round
at the very back of the head.
And um you can have it overlapping the
um back of the suit
a little bit.
That way it will look more like it's
part of the suit as opposed to being
detached. So keep it low and close to
the suit.
And when you're ready, you can sew it on
to the head.
Hope you really enjoy crocheting your
little star baby. If you like this
tutorial, please give me a thumbs up and
I'd love if you could subscribe for more
cute tutorials.
Happy crocheting. Bye now.
[music]
>> [music]